Guide to the Grover Francis Powers Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Grover Francis Powers papers
1911-1969
MS 1334
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.25
(4 boxes)
The papers of Grover Francis Powers contain correspondence, reports, writings, and a scrapbook. They document Powers' interest in mentally challenged children and involvement with the National Association for Retarded Children, the American Pediatric Society, and the Southbury Training School, as well as other organizations.
Powers, Grover Francis, 1887-1968
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Historical Medical Library, 1980.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Inventory, 1911-1969
Biographical / Historical
Grover Francis Powers was born in Colfax, Indiana, in 1887. He graduated from Purdue University in 1908 and from Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine in 1913. Following graduation, Powers remained in Baltimore, Maryland, as a resident pediatrician. In 1921, he was invited to the Yale University School of Medicine, where he would remain until his retirement in 1952. Between 1927 and 1952, he served as chairman of the department of pediatrics. Powers was instrumental in the foundation of the Southbury Training School for mentally retarded children. He also served as president of the American Pediatric Society and as chairman of the scientific advisory board of the National Association of Retarded Children. Powers was one of the first to propose humane treatment of the mentally challenged. He died on April 18, 1967.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Grover Francis Powers contain correspondence, reports, writings, and a scrapbook. They document Powers' interest in mentally challenged children and involvement with the National Association of Retarded Children, the American Pediatric Society, and Southbury Training School, as well as other organizations.
Medicine; Scrapbooks; Powers, Grover Francis, 1887-1968; American Pediatric Society; National Association for Retarded Children; Southbury Training School (Southbury, Conn.)
- Inventory, 1916-1969
  - American Pediatric Society [mailings and pamphlets related to annual meetings], 1954-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Academy of Pediatrics Committee on Medical Education, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Ad Hoc Committee to Study the Need for a Children's Medical Center as an Integral Part of The Johns Hopkins Medical Institutions" [report of findings, draft of report, and minutes], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Darrow, Daniel Cady and James Lawder Gamble [correspondence, articles, and documents relating to Powers' nomination of Darrow and Gamble for the Nobel Prize], 1929-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Personal [correspondence and biographical], 1929-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Yale [correspondence and budgets], 1925-1950 (Box 1, Folder 6 - 7)
  - Clinical notes, Circa 1930-1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "State of Connecticut Project Proposal for Mental Retardation Planning Grant", 1964 April-May (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Association for Retarded Children in Greater New Haven, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Southbury Training School
    - "Prospectus & Building Program for a New Training School for Mental Defectives at Southbury, Connecticut", 1937 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Printed materials, handbook, brochure, and clipping, 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Proposals, reports, resolutions, and budgets, 1957-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 14 - 15)
    - "Notes submitted by Medical members to The Commission to Study Laws and Facilities of Connecticut Pertaining to the Prevention, Care and Treatment of Mental Disease and Defect and Allied Problems, and to Make Recommendations Thereon", 1936 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "Prospectus and Building Program for a New Training School for Mental Defectives at Southbury, Connecticut", 1937 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Administrative documents [reports, correspondence, and related], 1954-1958 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Photograph of superintendents, 1940 or 1941 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - International Union for Child Welfare, 1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "Proposal for a Center for Research in Maternal and Child Health and in Human Development at the Albert Einstein College of Medicine-Bronx Municipal Hospital Center", 1962 June 15 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Documents relating to Powers' death, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - National Association for Retarded Children
    - "Policies and Constitution and By-Laws", 1966 January (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Children Limited [NARC newspaper], 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Research materials, source materials, minutes, reports, and correspondence, 1953-1963 (Box 2, Folder 25 - 26)
    - Clippings, brochures, printed matter, correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Research bulletins, minutes, reports, 1954-1962 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - "Directory of NARC Committees and Research Advisory Board", 1966 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - "Executive Committee of SRAB [Scientific Research Advisory Board] Meeting", 1962 May 25 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - "Agenda Executive Committee of SRAB Meeting", 1961 December 12 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Reports of Scientific Research Advisory Board, 1959-1962 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Applications and proposals, 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 33 - 36)
  - "Coeliac Disease," by Powers and Daniel C. Darrow, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Printed materials
    - General, 1930-1958 (Box 3, Folder 38 - 39)
    - Yale publications, 1949, 1957, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence and non-professional writings [also contains some clippings and photographs], 1916-1961 (Box 3, Folder 41 - 42)
  - Photograph album, 1936, undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Scrapbook: "1st Trip to Europe. June 10-1911-Sept. 25" (Box 4)